So today's דף daf is דף ה, daf hey, and we are
going to pick up at the bottom of דף ד עמוד ב.
daf daled amud beis. We'll start again from the two dots, גבוה
מעשרים אמה. gavoha me’esrim amah. So we're going back to the משנה
Mishnah that says that if the opening is higher than twenty אמות,
amos, it is invalid. And the גמרא Gemara says, האי גבוה מעשרים
אמה ובעי למעוטיה כמה ממעיט? hai gavoha me’esrim amah u’ba le’mato, kama
mema’it? So it's higher than twenty אמות amos and you want to
lower it, how much do you have to lower it? So the
גמרא Gemara very interestingly, very sort of, you know, humorously says, כמה
ממעיט? kama mema’it? How much do you lower? כמה דצריך, kama d’tzaric,
how much you have to. If it's twenty-five אמות, amos, you lower
five. If it's twenty-seven, you lower seven. אלא רחבו בכמה? ela rochvo
bekama? How wide? Now what does that mean how wide? So רש"י
Rashi and everybody says that what we're talking here is that the
way you lower it is not the, like, you know, is not
the obvious way of lowering the beam, but it's actually of raising
the floor. Now, the רי"ף Rif says it's about lowering the beam,
but the continuing discussion in the גמרא Gemara makes it clear it's
about raising the floor. So, Micha asked yesterday, well, would anybody say
there's a problem with lowering the beam? And it's interesting, right? The
רא"ש Rosh who disagrees with the רי"ף Rif on reading the גמרא
Gemara doesn't mention it. You look in the שולחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch,
the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch when it describes this case talks about
raising the floor, you know, he doesn't mention lowering the beam. Then
like the משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah in like one half a sentence
says, 'Oh, by the way, also if you want to lower the
beam, that also can work,' which is pretty funny because that's like
the obvious thing you would do. You have a beam too high,
you make a little peg and you lower it and you have
a place for it to rest a little lower. But for whatever
reason, we're discussing that rather than doing that, you're raising the floor.
So then the גמרא Gemara says like this: אלא רחבו בכמה? ela
rochvo bekama? If you want to raise the floor underneath the beam
so that the space between the floor and the beam is less
than twenty, how wide, how deep, let's say, does that do you
have to raise it? Right? So if you're, if you've got—I'll try
to do my three-dimensional drawing. Okay. If this is your מבוי mavoi
here, right? And your beam is like this.
That's your beam across the opening of your מבוי, mavoi, and you're
raising this floor, how deep in do you have to raise it?
Okay, so that the area underneath the beam, all right, is that
somewhat clear? That the area underneath the beam is less than twenty
אמות. amos. Okay, so you're raising the floor so that this is
only so that this is less than twenty. Okay, how deep into
the מבוי mavoi does that—does the lowering of the height have to
be? Yes.
Well, פשיטא, pishita, but it's not the
other
way around.
What? Oh, less than twenty. Yeah. Yeah, okay. Yeah.
Yeah, okay, yeah.
Well, פשיטא, pishita, but it's not completely obvious you could lower the
beam because you're drawing then also the picture in the picture book,
the—the beam is at the top of the walls of the—of the
מבוי. mavoi. Right, so you'd have to do something.
What's easier? To bang in a few—a few nails in the somewhere
midpoint in the מבוי mavoi and lower the beam or to raise
the floor?
But I could see someone saying—claiming that you can't lower the beam
because then it will be lower than the walls.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, but you can. Okay, which is why I made
that point. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this:
Okay, so אלא רחבו בכמה? ela rochvo bekama? How wide or how
deep, let's say, is the—you know, the area that you have to
raise of the floor? רב יוסף אמר טפח. Rav Yosef amar tefach.
רב יוסף Rav Yosef says a טפח. tefach.
אביי אמר ארבעה. Abaye amar arba’ah. אביי Abaye says four טפחים. tefachim.
So what's at the base? Now the beam itself only has to
be a טפח tefach wide. לימא בהא קמיפלגי? laima behai kamifligi? Maybe
this is what they are debating. דמאן דאמר טפח קסבר מותר להשתמש
תחת הקורה. de’man d’amar tefach kasavar mutar le’ishtamesh tachat hakorah. The one
that says a טפח tefach says you're allowed to use the space
underneath the beam. ומאן דאמר ארבעה קסבר אסור להשתמש תחת הקורה. u’man
d’amar arba’ah kasavar assur le’ishtamesh tachat hakorah. And the one that says
four says you're not allowed to use the space under the beam.
Now, what does that mean? So,
רש"י Rashi says—and this is actually a great גמרא Gemara because we
are now going to get into, for today's דף, daf, the—a really
nice conceptual with practical application discussion of how does the beam function?
How halachically conceptually, what is the role of the beam? You will
remember that in the opening discussion that why higher than twenty אמות
amos is no good, we basically had two opinions. One is that
if it's too high it cannot define a doorway, and the other
is if it's too high it can't be seen. So one is
the idea of היכר, heker, that the emphasis of the beam is
that it should be noticeable, and the other is that somehow it
should define a doorway, or it should define a—and that's going to
be translated as, because sometimes if you make a צורת הפתח, tzuras
hapesach, a doorway, we consider it like a wall. So the basic
two models here that we think about about what is the beam
functioning, how halachically do we define it, is קורה משום היכר, korah
mishum heker, or is it משום מחיצה? mishum mechitzah? Is it functioning
basically there just as a—something to notice, like a sign, or is
it there to serve as a type of a wall? So in
this case, in this issue, in this case, if it is there
because of מחיצה, mechitzah, right? So here
is—here is your קורה. korah. Okay. If
this is— that's going down, right, if this is your beam, right,
maybe I'll just do it like this. If this is my beam,
right, and this גמרא Gemara here is at the edge of my
מבוי, mavoi, is it the back, is it the back edge of
the beam that goes down and makes the wall, or the front
edge of the beam? And the difference between that is whether you
are allowed to use the area under the beam. If it's the
front edge of the beam, the one closest to the opening of
the מבוי, mavoi, then I can use the area under the beam.
If it's the back edge, right, then I can't, because the wall
ends at the back edge of the beam. Sort of like the
whole discussion of the thickness of the wall between the היכל Heichal
and the קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kadashim, like you know, whether it was
part of the קודש קדשים Kodesh Kadashim or not.
Two points on that. One is if it's the whole thing is
just to show as a sign that you're only allowed to carry
until here, like here begins the רשות הרבים.
reshut harabbim. That's exactly why I said that this is not the
היכר heker idea, this is the idea that it serves as a
wall.
Right, and then but if it's a wall, why can't you say
also the whole width of it, you know, so I
don't know why we would pick one over the other. But if
it's a wall, the whole idea is that we look at it
in a more formalistic way, and we don't say do you notice
it or not notice it, it's a more formalistic discussion. So therefore
if we have to be formalistic and say that this forms a
type of a wall, so which edge of it do we imagine
is sort of the wall?
The whole thing. In other words, I don't say like the front
part of this is the wall but the back part of it
isn't. What? The whole thickness of it?
Okay, well you know, you could also ask that question of a
wall. What's the is the space holes within the wall, are they
part of the רשות היחיד reshut hayachid or are they part of
the רשות הרבים? reshut harabbim? You could have that discussion. Okay, so
therefore that's the issue. So how does that fit into this debate?
If you say you're allowed to use the space under the edge
of the beam, right, then that means that the outside edge, the
edge you know closest to the opening of the מבוי mavoi is
what makes the wall. Okay, if that's true,
then you could be under the beam.
If here, this is the outside edge here is the wall, then
all you need to do is raise the one טפח tefach under
the beam because then
I could be this space is less than twenty and it's not
yet where you know, it's not yet the space where the beam
becomes functional. There's a space in the מבוי mavoi that is less
than twenty. Am I being clear about this? You see the point?
Okay, so if however I can't use the space under the beam
and the wall comes down here, it doesn't do me any good
to raise the space under the קורה. korah. The space under the
קורה korah isn't usable space anyway. I have to raise the space
into the מבוי. mavoi. So once anyway it has to be more
than a טפח, tefach, so the next sort of official size after
one טפח tefach is ארבעה טפחים. arba'ah tefachim. Okay, and that's how
you get that position.
Okay, so that's the גמרא Gemara says maybe that's the debate. לא,
Lo, not necessarily. דכולי עלמא קסבר מותר להשתמש תחת הקורה. Dechulei alma
kasavar mutar lehishtamesh tachat hakorah. Everybody could all you can use the
space under the beam. So why then should it not be enough
to just raise the one טפח tefach underneath the beam?
ובהא קמיפלגי, Uveha kamiflagi, this is the debate. מר סבר קורה משום
היכר ומר סבר קורה משום מחיצה. Mar savar korah mishum heker umar
savar korah mishum mechitza. Again, very nicely articulating two models for what
the קורה korah is. One says it's about a wall and one
says it's about a היכר. heker. Now, why would that how would
that play out? So if it's because of a
היכר, heker, so
one minute let me just check רש"י Rashi a minute.
Right, so here you could have sort of gone either way, which
is what I was double-checking רש"י, Rashi, but if it's because of
היכר, heker, so as long as the space under the beam is
less than twenty, so when I am under the beam I can
look up and still see the beam, right, because the idea of
less than twenty would be that it would be visible. If however
it's because of מחיצה, mechitza, so normally in if you have to
say that you have a the idea of a מחיצה mechitza is
to define a space surrounded by walls. So the minimum size of
a space normally when we say some space surrounded by walls is
a ארבעה טפחים arba'ah tefachim space. Normally when we describe like an
area, anything less than ארבעה טפחים arba'ah tefachim by ארבעה טפחים arba'ah
tefachim is not a significant area. Sometimes we even want ארבע אמות
arba amot by ארבע אמות, arba amot, but minimally we want ארבעה
טפחים arba'ah tefachim by ארבעה טפחים. arba'ah tefachim. Okay, so now you're
saying that the difference is is that if all I have to
do if the whole reason it has to be less than twenty
is I have to be able to look up and see it,
then as long as here while I'm on the threshold I will
be able to look up and see it's less than twenty, that's
enough, and you only need a טפח. tefach. If however the idea
is to define this as a wall, so what I really by
defining this as a wall is I'm saying is I have to
create four walls around it, but I can't have a walls need
a space the walls can't be higher than twenty, or at least
this wall can't be higher than twenty, I need to have a
significant space. I need to go deeper in so I have a
significant space that is surrounded by walls.
So you make your wall more wally?
Well, not
yeah, because walls solid or is it just like four pegs? It's
an imaginary wall.
It's an imaginary wall. Right, okay, yeah.
When we deal with עירובין Eruvin and סוכה Sukkah I'm always reminded
of the scene from, what is it, what's that movie, I think
I mentioned this before,
Space something,
Spaceballs. Was it Spaceballs? I think so. Anyway, it was like a
spoof on one of these space movies. Anyway, and anyway this group
of people they were like running and running away from something and
then they banged, there was nothing there but they like crashed into
something you couldn't see. He says, "What is this?" He says, "That's
an imaginary, that's an invisible wall." He says, "Oh, I always wondered
what an invisible wall would look like." Okay. So you have a
lot of invisible walls going on here. All right,
yeah.
If you say a הכשר, hechsher, I mean again, it's not, it's
still formalized, I mean you can't just like have a sign there
and no קורה. korah. Right.
Okay, but the question we ask is once you satisfy the criteria,
then to test whether various things work within the context of קורה,
korah, the key question will be: is it noticeable? So since it's
noticeable underneath, that would suffice. Okay, so that's what the גמרא Gemara
says: מר סבר קורה משום הכר, mar savar korah mishum heker, that
it's הכר, heker, so therefore if it's noticeable underneath that's enough, ומר
סבר קורה משום מחיצה, umar savar korah mishum mechitza, the other says
it's because of a wall and מחיצות mechitzas have to be minimally
around a space that is four by four טפחים tefachim because a
רשות היחיד reshut hayachid for example is defined, what's the basic definition
of רשות היחיד? reshut hayachid? Four by four טפחים tefachim with four
walls around it. So therefore you need at least four טפחים. tefachim.
Okay. ואיבעית אימא, ve’iba’it eima, and if you want you could say,
דכולי עלמא קורה משום הכר, dechulei alma korah mishum heker, everybody would
agree that it's because of a הכר. heker. הכא בהכר שמטה ובהכר
שמעלה קמיפלגי. hacha beheker shemata uveheker shemala kamiflegi. The question is: noticeable
below and noticeable above? מר סבר אמרינן הכר שמטה כהכר שמעלה. mar
savar amrinan heker shemata keheker shemala.
The same way above, how big does the wall have to be,
the קורה korah have to be? Only a טפח. tefach. So if
we only require a טפח tefach thickness above, then we only require
a טפח tefach of space below that you can notice the קורה,
korah, right? Because if you say even if you say it's because
of הכר, heker, who says it's enough that I just notice it
when I'm directly underneath it? Maybe I have to be able to
notice it even when I'm into the מבוי, mavoi, right? It's a
little funny to say that
it's only required to be situated in a way that can be
noticed when you're directly underneath it, right? That maybe that's not sufficient.
So everybody agrees it's a הכר. heker. The one that says a
טפח tefach suffices says הכר שמטה כהכר שמעלה. heker shemata keheker shemala.
The same way above we only need a טפח, tefach, then below
we only need you to be able to notice it within a
טפח tefach width when you're directly underneath it. ומר סבר, umar savar,
and the other says: לא אמרינן הכר שמטה כהכר שמעלה. lo amrinan
heker shemata keheker shemala. No, although above it only has to be
a טפח tefach wide, below you have to be able to see
it
more distant. You'd have to be able to see it coming up
to it, not just when you are directly underneath it.
Or you could go the other way around, maybe הכר שמעלה heker
shemala is more important than, I have no idea.
Okay, so that's a third possibility. ואיבעית אימא, ve’iba’it eima, one minute,
a fourth possibility: דכולי עלמא אמרינן הכר שמטה כהכר שמעלה. dechulei alma
amrinan heker shemata keheker shemala. Really
it would be enough to notice it when you're directly underneath it.
Okay, והכא בגזירה שמא
יפחות קמיפלגי. vehacha begzeira shema yifchos kamiflegi. It's a simple secondary concern,
I mean דרבנן, derabbanan, but here it's a secondary concern. If we
let you do one טפח, tefach, maybe it'll easily become less than
one טפח. tefach. So we make you do a larger size so
that you do four טפחים tefachim so it'll never get to be
less than one טפח. tefach. Okay. So anyway, so very interestingly what
we have here is framed and this is like a very nice
key סוגיא sugya right at the beginning and interestingly parallels the discussion
at the beginning whether twenty אמות ammot is learned from the idea
of a doorway, which is sort of like the
מחיצה mechitza idea, or is it just because of what will be
noticeable. So here we have those two models as it plays out
to this question. If it's because of a wall, you would need
four טפחים tefachim of space surrounded by walls. If it's because of
הכר, heker, then you can debate: is it enough to have a
הכר heker directly underneath it, do you need a הכר heker for
more distance, and those are the possibilities. Yes, Charlie?
If the area you raised meets the right definitions, it might be
a מקום פטור. makom patur.
Surrounded by four walls?
No, whether surrounded by walls or not.
No, you don't have a מקום פטור makom patur surrounded by walls.
I mean not if it's four by four טפחים. tefachim.
Yeah, what if it's less than four by?
Yeah, right. But that, but you don't want to be doing that.
You want to be creating a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. I mean
it's true, you, yeah.
Does anyone say that if you make your קורה korah too wide
then it loses the הכר heker because then it just looks like?
Yeah, well we'll get to something like that coming up.
Okay, so that was the case when it was higher than twenty
אמות. ammot. Now we go to the reverse case. We have a
יתיבי itayvei that it can't be less than ten טפחים, tefachim, but
we are saying that now: היה פחות מעשרה טפחים. haya pachot measarah
tefachim.
So let's say it was a very short מבוי, mavoi, okay, or
maybe
even... I mean I don't really have to draw that because it
wasn't drawn to scale but anyway let's say you know your מבוי
mavoi was surrounded by low walls. Okay now these are 10 so
now maybe but now these I guess 10 טפחים tefachim walls they
have to be 10 because or else it wouldn't be a it
wouldn't be a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. But when it gets towards
let's say you know towards the towards the edge of it let's
say the wall drops. Okay towards the edge of it. So now
here right the height of the קורה korah is only let's say
8 טפחים tefachim from the ground. Okay that's too short. Now it's
pretty funny that it's too short because of היכר heker because you
would think that you would obviously see it because you'd have to
walk into it which is again maybe an indication that that it
has to some degree satisfy the idea of a wall as well.
We'll see in a minute when we turn the page תוספות Tosafot
makes the reverse point. Even if it was because of a wall
there has to to some degree be היכר heker components as well
so it's not all black or white. But the הלכה halachah is
is that the קורה korah cannot be less than 8 okay so
היה פחות מעשרה hayah pachot mei'asarah if it was I mean cannot
be less than 10. If it was less than 10 טפחים tefachim
וחקק בו להשלימו לעשרה. vechakak bo lehashlimo le'asarah. So again rather than
you doing something to raise the beam you dug into the ground
and you made a pit so that now the space right below
the right by the opening of the מבוי mavoi was you know
was deeper was lower and therefore it was a 10 טפח tefach
height. It's just the reverse case. Rather than creating a mound you
dug a pit. So כמה חוקק kamah chokek how deep how much
do you have to dig? So again the גמרא Gemara says כמה
חוקק kamah chokek how much do you dig? כמה דצריך kamah ditzrich
as much as you need. So if it was 8 טפחים tefachim
you dig 2 טפחים tefachim if it was 7 you dig 3.
So the גמרא Gemara says אלא ela okay
משכו בכמה? mashcho bechamah? Again how deep do you have to dig
do you have to dig the pit? The exact same question right
except it's rather than the mound it's the pit. How wide well
I meant by deeper I mean so you're now going to dig
a what? Yeah you're now going to dig a 2 טפח tefach
a 2 טפח tefach pit. How deep into the מבוי mavoi do
you have to dig it? Directly under the קורה korah more into
the מבוי mavoi 1 טפח tefach 4 טפחים? tefachim? Okay how how
deep into the מבוי mavoi do you have to dig the pit?
Yeah yeah you could raise the if you want to make a
pit I understand. These are yeah these are interesting theoretical questions. I
don't think that if you had this situation you'd much more obviously
raise the thing you know raise or lower the beam than actually
change the floor space of your מבוי mavoi but okay.
Well this question we've given them before.
Well let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. Okay so you
would think it would be the same debate but interestingly there are
different opinions. רב יוסף אמר בארבעה ואביי אמר בארבע אמות. Rav Yosef
amar be'arba'ah ve'Abaye amar be'arba amot. רב יוסף Rav Yosef says 4
טפחים tefachim and אביי Abaye says 4 אמות amot and nobody takes
the 1 טפח tefach position. Let's see what this is about.
לימא בדרבי אמי ודרבי אסי קמיפלגי? Leima bid'Rabbi Ami uvid'Rabbi Assi kamipalgi?
Let's say they're debating whether they hold like רבי אמי Rabbi Ami
and רבי אסי. Rabbi Assi. דאתמר De'itmar it was said מבוי שנפרץ
מצדו כלפי ראשו. mavoi shenifratz mitzido kelapi rosho. So if you have
a מבוי mavoi that was that was broken at its on the
side near the opening of it. אתמר משמיה דרבי אמי ורבי אסי
Itmar mishmei d'Rabbi Ami ve'Rabbi Assi so it was said in the
name of רבי אמי Rabbi Ami and רבי אסי Rabbi Assi אם
יש פס ארבעה מתיר בפרצה עד עשר im yesh pas arba'ah matir
bepirtzah ad eser ואם לאו ve'im lav if there's a
if there is a if there's a piece a plank I guess
that's a better word for a פס pas anyway
but a partition a part of the wall that is left that
is 4 טפחים tefachim then you can be okay even if the
rest even if the break is 10 אמות amot wide. It's complicated
because it switches from טפחים tefachim to אמות. amot. So let' first
explain that and then I'll get to the second part. So רש"י
Rashi has the if you look at the רש"י Rashi in the
lower right not at the very bottom the first picture in רש"י
Rashi he has the picture. I mean here I'll just draw it.
Okay you have your מבוי mavoi right like this it had its
three walls but then what happened is and it has that you
now had a break in this wall. Okay when does it become
a problem? Now if it's this was particularly an issue because it's
a break near the head of the מבוי mavoi and this wall
and it has to extend you have to extend to the end
of the מבוי mavoi because that's where you're going to put your
beam right? So the wall has to be seen as extending. So
if this part in the front is 4 טפחים tefachim okay then
this is considered enough of a legitimate space in the front of
the מבוי. mavoi. And then even up to 10 אמות amot will
be okay because as we learned in our first משנה mishnah this
is a general principle up to 10 אמות amot is considered to
be an opening and not a break. Okay if it's so up
to 10 אמות amot you can incorporate a hole up to 10
אמות. amot. But it can't be 10 אמות amot all the way
to the end because you need the space here to have to
be surrounded by walls. Okay so that's the first position. אם יש
שם פס ארבעה im yesh sham pas arba'ah if there's a 4
טפח tefach partition מתיר בפרצה עד עשר matir bepirtzah ad eser then
you can allow the rest of to the break to be up
to ten אמות. amot. ואם
לאו ve'im lav and if it's not פחות משלושה pachot mishlosha if
it's you don't have a four טפח tefach partition in the beginning
up the front, פחות משלושה מתיר, pachot mishlosha matir, שלושה אינו מתיר
shlosha eino matir then the only thing that would be okay would
be if you have a gap of less than three. If you
don't have four טפח tefach up front, so then you can only
you have a little bit done, you have a two טפח tefach
piece up front, you can only manage if this gap is less
than three טפחים tefachim because less than three we view it as
continuous. But anything that would be more than three טפחים tefachim then
it would not be connected to the wall and you would only
be having you would have an orphan two טפח tefach wall there.
Do you understand? If you need to have a four a real
four טפח tefach wall up front and if you don't have a
four physical טפח tefach wall up front, only two, the only way
it's going to work is if you use the לבוד lavud and
see it as continuous. But if you have it as an orphan,
if this is more than three right? טפח, tefach, so this is
orphan here and it's not a four טפח tefach in the front
then it's not valid. So the upshot of all of that is
you need to have four walls up in front. Yes.
What if for that parallel סוכה sukka for instance? You know, you
only have to
have like two walls and a bit like we see... Let's not
We'll talk later about comparing סוכה sukka cases. Let's worry about each
case on its own. Okay. So לרב יוסף אית ליה דרב אמי
לרב אביי לית ליה דרב אמי. le-Rav Yosef it lei de-Rav Ami
le-Rav Abaye leit lei de-Rav Ami. Rav
Yosef holds of Rav Ami and says okay so you see four
טפחים tefachim is enough and that's why I say four טפחים tefachim
is enough. Abaye doesn't hold of Rav Ami. So what the גמרא
Gemara is assuming here is I tried to make the case too
easy because what the גמרא Gemara is assuming here is that
I was cheating. Okay so is that let's say the entire thing
is less okay than ten טפחים. tefachim. So what you by digging
what you're doing is not only helping the space under the קורה,
kora, you're actually creating ten טפח tefach walls into the entire מבוי.
mavoi. Right? Is that clear? Because if this is less than ten
טפחים tefachim then it means that these walls are less than ten
טפחים tefachim and those are not halachic walls. Is that clear? The
whole walls everything. So by digging you're actually making the side walls
also into halachic walls because you are lowering the ground and making
them ten טפחים. tefachim. So how much wall how much you need
halachic walls at the very front of the מבוי. mavoi. So one
says four טפחים tefachim and maybe Abaye disagrees and Abaye would say
you need four אמות. amot. Four טפחים tefachim is not enough. So
let's see. What? I'm sorry?
Then the wall would fall apart if you dug under the wall.
Oh you worry about such little things.
Let's not worry about practically whether this works. Okay so anyway let's
take a look.
One minute. Okay let me just check one thing.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says one one minute.
Yeah I just want to see.
It could be high anyway you're like crawling under it or something?
They're all high at ten טפח. tefach.
Okay
so the גמרא Gemara says like this, so the גמרא Gemara says
לרב אביי
לית ליה דרב אמי. le-Rav Abaye leit lei de-Rav Ami. אמר לך
אביי, amar lach Abaye, so Abaye will say to you התם סוף
מבוי הכא תחילת מבוי. hatam sof mavoi hacha techilat mavoi. No there's
a difference. I could go even like Rav Ami and Rav Assi.
There they're talking about that there was a break. You started with
a good מבוי mavoi so there's a general rule, I'll read this
like תוספות Tosafot reads it, there's a general rule that it's easier
for something to retain a status than it is to gain a
status. Okay? So therefore when you started with when you started in
that case with real walls maybe you only need four טפחים tefachim
left at the beginning to consider it to be legitimate for the
configuration. But here where you did not start with legitimate walls and
by digging you're creating walls you need a larger area to be
considered to be the area surrounded by walls in order in order
to begin. So that's what he says: התם hatam what read
that אמר לך אביי סוף מבוי, amar lach Abaye sof mavoi, there
it's what it's the remnants of a it's the end of the
process. You're left with the walls. So you can satisfy as long
as you have four טפחים tefachim in the beginning. הכא תחילת מבוי,
hacha techilat mavoi, here you're trying to create a מבוי. mavoi. אי
איכא ארבע אמות אין אי לאו לאו. i ika arba amot in
i lav lav. If there's four אמות amot yes, if not, not.
And now this gets to an interesting conceptual question which Abaye will
turn to because Abaye will say: what is the basic minimum size
of a מבוי mavoi that you can consider this space at the
beginning to be like a mini-מבוי? mini-mavoi? If you are digging and
only the space at the beginning is surrounded by walls as walls
of ten טפחים tefachim then you have to basically say that that
actually is considered to be a מבוי mavoi is considered a מבוי
mavoi by itself because the other space doesn't have those walls. So
Abaye's argument of four אמות amot as we're going to see is
that you need four אמות amot in order to make a space
considered to be a מבוי. mavoi. You can't have a
מבוי. mavoi. Yeah, for now we'll assume that. So now let's take
a look what the גמרא Gemara says. So אמר לו, Amar Lo,
so אביי Abaye says, four טפחים tefachim there are what? Because you
had a full מבוי mavoi and it was just something that broke
off, but to start you need four אמות. amot. איכא
דאמרי סיני לה לא. Ika DeAmrei Sini Leh Lo. אמר אביי, Amar
Abaye, so אביי Abaye now אביי Abaye gets his
up-at-bat. אמינא מנא ליה, Amina Mana Lei, where do I say four
אמות amot is the idea? דתניא, Detanya, we taught in the ברייתא,
Baraita, אין
מבוי ניתר בלחי וקורה Ein mavoi niter beLechi veKora עד שיהיו בתים
וחצרות פתוחים לתוכו. ad sheyihyu Batim veChatzeirot ptuchim letocho. So a מבוי
mavoi can only be allowed with a לחי Lechi or a קורה,
Kora, either a לחי Lechi is a vertical and a קורה Kora
is a horizontal beam, so meaning you don't need a real fourth
wall, one little marker is enough, but that's only if it has
a status of a מבוי. mavoi. What is needed to have a
status of a מבוי? mavoi? That you have to have
בתים Batim opening up into yards, and yards opening up into the
מבוי. mavoi. Basically the basic configuration as I told you the other
day is that you had courts, you had multiple houses, right, that
would open up into a חצר. chatzer. Okay, you had houses opened
up into a חצר, chatzer, and then you had multiple חצרות, chatzeirot,
right, courts that opened up into a מבוי, mavoi, which was like
a type of an alleyway or a communal courtyard. Alright, so what
he is saying is we will only give a מבוי mavoi the
allowance to use either the לחי, Lechi, the vertical, or the קורה,
Kora, the horizontal. It only has a status of a מבוי mavoi
if you have two houses opening up into a courtyard, and here
two houses, you have to have בתים פתוחים לחצר וחצרות פתוחות למבוי.
Batim ptuchim lechatzer vechatzeirot ptuchot lemavoi. So basically you have to have
at least two courtyards opening into it for it to have the
status of a מבוי. mavoi. And each courtyard has to have two
houses opening into them. Alright?
So you think you put a comma after בתים? Batim? Is that
what it... in other words could it also mean or could he
mean that the house could be open directly to the מבוי? mavoi?
That's not how I, mean I don't know, yeah that's not how
it's read. I mean it's not me, it's I mean I'm following
רש"י. Rashi. I don't know if anybody suggests that. But no, but
it's read that you have to have בתים פתוחים, Batim ptuchim, where
is it, עד שיהיו בתים וחצרות... ad sheyihyu Batim veChatzeirot... right,
I see your point. Because the literal... it says בתים וחצרות פתוחים
לתוכו. Batim veChatzeirot ptuchim letocho. But no, in other places it's clear
that it means בתים פתוחים לחצרות וחצרות פתוחות למבוי. Batim ptuchim lechatzeirot
vechatzeirot ptuchot lemavoi. Now, ואי, Ve'ee, so now here's אביי's Abaye argument,
one minute, and if you don't have that, it doesn't have a
status of a מבוי. mavoi. And if it doesn't, then you need
something more significant on the fourth side, which we'll talk about in
a minute. ואי בארבעה היכי משכחת לה? Ve'ee bearba'ah heichi mashkachat lah?
So here's אביי's Abaye question: Look, the idea of opening is always
minimally four טפחים. tefachim. So if this is your מבוי, mavoi,
and you're saying theoretically you could have a minimum length of a
מבוי mavoi four טפחים, tefachim, because that's the argument, you have to
only go in four טפחים, tefachim, so conceptually a מבוי mavoi can
be only four טפחים tefachim in its length. So I don't get
it, he says, where are the house... where is the courtyard going
to open? If this is a חצר chatzer and this is a
חצר, chatzer, and we consider that an opening has to be four
טפחים, tefachim, then there's going to be no walls there. Okay, you
see? Because an opening means no walls. So where are they going
to open? Now you can't say, now you'll be... you'll say oh
but maybe it's like very wide. Maybe it's like very wide here
and it's only four טפחים tefachim deep, and the חצרות chatzeirot open
this way. Right? You're going to suggest that? Yeah. But the הלכה
halacha is that to have a status of a מבוי mavoi it
has to be length greater than width.
Okay?
So if this is four טפחים, tefachim, then this has to be
less than four טפחים. tefachim. So where are... or at least not
more. Okay, so less than or equal to, okay, we'll worry about
equal later. Anyway, so where are the חצרות chatzeirot going to open
up into? There's going to be no wall left anywhere the חצרות
chatzeirot open up into. So what are you going to... so that's
אביי Abaye says, so clearly a minimum מבוי mavoi has to have
four אמות, amot, or you could never have this configuration with חצרות
chatzeirot opened up to a מבוי mavoi that's four טפחים. tefachim. So
he says,
וכי תימא, V'khi Teima, so I should have just said the next
line of the גמרא, Gemara, דפתח לה בדופן אמצעית, DePatach lah bedofan
emtza'it, maybe you open the courtyards in the back wall and you
have a very long back wall. ואמר רב נחמן, Ve'amar Rav Nachman,
נקטינן, Nakti'nan, רב נחמן Rav Nachman says, we take the position: איזהו
מבוי שניתר בלחי וקורה? Eizehu mavoi sheniter beLechi veKora? Again, what is
a מבוי mavoi that it's enough to have a לחי Lechi or
a קורה, Kora, that we allow something minimal for the fourth wall?
כל שארכו יתר על רחבו. Kol she'orko yeter al rochbo. You might
say that's the definition of length, but no, because you know, it's
if you think about it like think about it as a street.
Length is sort of the direction in which the street runs. Okay,
so anyway it has to have the length greater than the width.
So if this is enough to have four טפחים, tefachim, then this
has to be less than four טפחים. tefachim. Where are the courtyards
going to open up into? There's going to be no wall left.
So the גמרא Gemara
says, ורב יוסף, VeRav Yosef, what would רב יוסף Rav Yosef say?
דפתח לה בקרן זוית. DePatach lah bekeren zavit. They open into the
corner. So if you take a look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi
gives you, you see the lower right hand picture in
רש"י? Rashi? Okay. Basically the way he's drawing it in is that
they open up rather than opening straight, the opening looks like this.
Okay? So this and therefore there's a little wall that's left here
at the bottom. Okay, because you can get four טפחים tefachim at
an angle and still leave over a little bit at the bottom.
Do you see that? Right? Because at an angle it doesn't need
as much as if it's straight. Okay, so of course if you
actually do the math, you know how you do the math? No,
it does work out. You know the math works, a squared plus
b squared equals c squared. So what, how long would this, this
can only be up to two, right? So how long would this
have to be to get this to be four? And it basically
is about 3.5, I think, or maybe 3.7. I did the math,
it's a lot. Okay, because
רש"י Rashi implies that it's a square root of two, it's a
45 degree angle. That's not true. But you're basically left with like
a third of a טפח tefach at the bottom. But you can
get a little piece of wall, says רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, if
it's at an angle. So that's theoretically how you would do it.
But אביי's Abaye position is starting to sound much more attractive, right?
Because אביי's Abaye position is that it is not considered a מבוי
mavoi until it is four אמות, amos, which A, makes intuitive sense,
whoever heard of a street that's only four טפחים tefachim long?
And B, certainly works in terms of this argument because this way
you're only left with a tiny remnant of a wall.
The vertex doesn't have to be in the middle, so you can
have uneven sides.
Oh, now you've got me confused. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says, alright, so אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, so אביי's Abaye going to
have another, another up at bat. מנא אמינא לה, Mina amina lah,
here's another way I can prove it. Where do I get this
from? דאמר רמי בר חמא אמר רב הונא לחי הבולט מדופנו של
מבוי פחות מארבע אמות נידון משום לחי ואינו צריך לחי אחר להתירו.
De'amar Rami Bar Chama amar Rav Huna: Lechi habolet midofno shel mavoi,
pachas me'arba amos, nidon mishum lechi ve'eino tzarich lechi acher lehatiro. Okay,
so now, Michael, this is somewhat related to your question.
There is a famous מחלוקת אביי ורבא machlokes Abaye v'Rava about לחי
העומד מאליו. lechi ha'omed me'eilav. A לחי lechi that stands by, that
was put up by itself. Doesn't literally mean that, but it means
that you have something that functionally can serve as a לחי lechi
but was never put there for the purpose of a לחי. lechi.
A good example might be a telephone pole. But let's say that
when you were configuring your מבוי mavoi here, you decided that you
actually wanted to have a little thing inserted like that for who
knows what reason, okay, and the wall went in a little bit.
So that's לחי העומד מאליו, lechi ha'omed me'eilav, it was never put
there to be the לחי. lechi. And now you want to say,
oh can I use it as a לחי? lechi?
So, מחלוקת אביי ורבא. machlokes Abaye v'Rava. אביי Abaye says you can,
רבא Rava says you can't. It's one of the few cases that
we rule like
אביי. Abaye.
Is it part of your walls or something separate?
It doesn't matter. Okay, and אביי Abaye says you can use it,
and we're assuming you can use it. Wait, so let's keep on
reading.
So, לחי הבולט מדופנו של מבוי. lechi habolet midofno shel mavoi. So
it's sticking out, but it's the, somehow, it wasn't put there purposely
for that. פחות מארבע אמות נידון משום לחי. pachas me'arba amos nidon
mishum lechi. Less than four אמות amos it can serve as a
לחי. lechi. That's לחי העומד מאליו. lechi ha'omed me'eilav. ואינו צריך לחי
אחר להתירו, ve'eino tzarich lechi acher lehatiro, and you don't need another
לחי, lechi, that is the לחי. lechi. ארבע אמות, arba amos, once
it's four אמות, amos, נידון משום מבוי. nidon mishum mavoi. Then it's
considered to just be a wall of the מבוי. mavoi. וצריך לחי
אחר להתירו, v'tzarich lechi acher lehatiro, and it needs another לחי lechi
to make it permissible. So,
it's a very bizarre idea because you would think as it gets
longer it should make it only better. But the idea is once
it gets to be too long, then it cannot, then it's just,
this works particularly if you think the idea of לחי lechi is
a היכר. heker. Okay, once it gets to be too long, it's
considered just like the wall of the מבוי, mavoi, and as a
wall of the מבוי mavoi it's not a לחי, lechi, it's a
wall. So you need another לחי lechi by the לחי. lechi. Okay?
Now, now the question you might be asking is, heck, if that's
a wall, let me just consider that as the rest of the
wall there. Okay, but you have too big of a gap, and
the גמרא Gemara will discuss why cases in which you can end
the wall. But assuming you consider once it gets too big and
you consider it a wall and not the לחי, lechi, it needs
another לחי lechi to make it permissible. Now how does this prove
אביי's Abaye case? So let me just double check רש"י Rashi make
sure I'm saying this right.
Yeah, so
hold on.
Yeah, it's not exactly clear to me because,
oh no, I'm sorry. Okay, I got it, I got it, I
got it. Okay, sorry, I just forgot my central point. So the
point is like this. The point is, why does, why by four
אמות amos is it considered to be no longer a לחי? lechi?
Because אביי Abaye would say, because what are you doing? Because essentially
what you're saying is that you have here your own, your own
מבוי mavoi already. Okay, once it's four אמות. amos. So you see
that the reason the... What's its ארבע אמות four amot it stops
being a לחי lechi is because is that a width of four
אמות four amot can define a length of can define the configuration
of a מבוי. mavoi. So according to you, רב יוסף, Rav Yosef,
even four טפחים tefachim
defines a מבוי, mavoi, why don't we say it stops being a
לחי lechi and starts being something else once it's four טפחים tefachim
wide? That's אביי'ס Abaye's challenge and let's read רב יוסף'ס Rav Yosef's
answer. רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, and רב יוסף Rav Yosef will say
back, לאפוקי מתורת לחי עד דאיכא ארבע אמות. lafukei mitorat lechi ad
de'ika arba amot. No, no, no. Look, if something basically is functioning
as a לחי, lechi, I'm not going to redefine it once it's,
you know, until it's significantly different, until it's
four אמות. four amot. דמהוי מבוי, demihavi mavoi, but when you're talking
about the basic parameters of a מבוי, mavoi, אפילו בארבעה טפחים נמי
הוי
מבוי, afilu bearba tefachim nami havi mavoi, even by four טפחים, tefachim,
because the basic point is look, this thing to be considered a
לחי, lechi, we are going to say that just objectively by the
way it's structured, it's a wall and it's not a לחי. lechi.
I'm not going to make that claim until it's a significant length.
Okay, but that doesn't mean that at a smaller space wouldn't be
the parameters of a מבוי, mavoi, but it's nevertheless that the fact
that you've made it wide enough for the parameters of a מבוי
mavoi isn't going to change its identity until it's significantly longer.
Only regards to the לחי lechi you were saying it has to
be a certain
only regards to the if
we're talking about a לחי lechi that's an actual wall then is
that what he's saying?
No. What he is saying is that they're different questions. The question
we asked is what is the minimum width of a, you know,
what are the minimum
dimensions of a, right, of a our question was, where do you
put the קורה? korah? How deep do you have to dig it?
So what's the minimum length of a, you know, of a
מבוי? mavoi? And אביי Abaye says four טפחים four tefachim
and four אמות four amot and רב יוסף Rav Yosef says four
טפחים. four tefachim. So here we're trying to prove that question of
the minimum based on when this stops being a קורה korah and
starts being considered a wall. Assuming, the assumption we're making is that
that point of transition is once you've hit the width of the
מבוי. mavoi. And רב יוסף'ס Rav Yosef's answer back is I don't
agree with that assumption. Here you're changing its identity from a קורה
korah to a wall, it needs only when it hits a certain
length. But maybe, but he says that that's related to the question
about the minimum sort of size of a מבוי. mavoi. So, so
the thing that bothers me though is that I don't know okay
forget it
is that here we're talking about width and not length, but it
goes into the fact that a מבוי'ס mavoi's length and width are
related. So if the width is four yes, exactly so that's the
point. That's what had gotten me confused for a moment. Here if
the width, if four stops being is considered too wide, you know,
the width and that proves also that the length is because the
length is always greater than the width. So אביי'ס Abaye's argument is,
if once it hits four אמות four amot it exceeds the minimum
width, then that shows that the length has to be at least
four אמות. four amot. Is that clear? No? Yes? I got everybody
confused? Remember we said a מבוי mavoi is defined that the length
is greater than the width, right? So here if we see that
the width once it hits four אמות four amot it's no longer
it already has exceeded the width of the,
you know, it's already the minimum width of the מבוי, mavoi, so
that shows you that the length, the minimum width has to be
at least four אמות. four amot.
But the remaining area that you dashed out there would not be
a מבוי mavoi because the length would be
no, the length would be greater than the width. It would be
fine.
If אביי Abaye can prove the width has to be four אמות
four amot then certainly the length has to be four אמות. four
amot. Okay, that's the whole point. All right. All right. Moving on.
Now you're getting a feel of what עירובין Eruvin is like. גופא.
Gufa.
I'm going to be left wondering if I could explain it better,
but I'm doing the best I
can. גופא. Gufa. In the time that I've got. Question is how
are we going to deal with it with שבת Shabbos where we
can't draw. Okay. Now.
Okay, so basically what we
have, so let me just distill what we've got. The first debate
is, which is one we're going to see throughout, is is a
קורה korah a type of a wall or is it a הכר?
heker? And if it's a wall, is it the inner part of
the קורה korah or the outer part? Or is it basically a
הכר? heker? Here the question is what's the minimum size of a
מבוי? mavoi? four טפחים four tefachim or four אמות? four amot? four
אמות four amot obviously makes a lot more intuitive sense. Okay, and
that issue is therefore how far, how much digging you have to
dig in order to get walls for the first four טפחים four
tefachim or the walls for the first four אמות. four amot. גופא.
Gufa. Now let's look at this issue here about when the לחי
lechi turns into a wall. This actually I think is an easier
issue. אמר רמי בר חמא אמר רב הונא לחי הבולט מדופנו של
מבוי. amar Rami bar Chama amar Rav Huna lechi habolet midofno shel
mavoi.
So the לחי lechi is sticking out. פחות מארבע אמות pachot mearba
amot I guess we weren't going to finish okay, thankfully because it's
difficult, the דף daf is more short also. פחות מארבע אמות נידון
משום לחי. pachot mearba amot nido mishum lechi. Less than four אמות
four amot it's still a לחי lechi and אין צריך לחי אחר
להתירו, ein tzarich lechi acher lehatiro, you don't need another לחי. lechi.
ארבע אמות, arba amot, once it's four אמות, four amot, then it
becomes considered like a wall, so
it's משום מבוי, mishum mavoi, it's like an extension of the מבוי
mavoi wall, וצריך לחי אחר להתירו, vetzarich lechi acher lehatiro, and you
need another
לחי. lechi. If he put it next to the extension, let's say
you put it next to the extension, אוסופי הוא דקא מוסיף לה.
osei hu dikamosif la. So now instead of having a four אמה
amah extension, you have a four אמה amah and one טפח tefach
extension, okay? How have you made it better? It's the same length.
So that might be the answer.
So but initially the גמרא Gemara says, if you just put the
לחי lechi here, so wonderful, so how's that made it better? Once
it's ארבע אמות arba amot it stops being a לחי, lechi, another
לחי lechi is just going to make it a bigger wall. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב פפה, Amar Rav Pappa, דמוקי לה
לאידך גיסא. demokei lei le'idach gisa. Fine, put it against the other
wall. רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua אמר,
amar, like Michael says, אפילו תימא דמוקי לה בהדיא, Afilu teima demokei
lei behadei, even if you put it as an extension of this
wall, דמטפי ביה או דמבצרי ביה, dematzpi bei o demabtzri bei, you
make it a little more, a little less. And more or less
could be in either of the other two dimensions, either to be
higher or lower, or it could be deeper or not as deep.
So in the other two dimensions it could be a little bit
different and that's enough for a היכר. heker. Okay. אמר רב הונא,
Amar Rav Huna, so said רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, Rav Huna
brei d'Rav Yehoshua, לא אמרין אלא במבוי שמונה. lo amrin ela bemavoy
shemoneh. This whole thing that it's a problem once it hits ארבע
אמות arba amot is only if the מבוי mavoy is שמונה shemoneh
or bigger. אבל במבוי שבע, Aval bemavoy shiva, which means anything less
than seven... sorry eight...
eight אמות amot wide or bigger.
But if it's seven or less, I mean seven really means anything
less than eight, ניתר באמה מרובה על הפרוץ. niter b'amah meruba al
haparutz. It's allowed because basically it becomes a wall. He says look,
if this is ארבע אמות arba amot and this whole length here
is
seven point nine,
okay, that's the basic point, then the majority of this wall is
closed off, okay, and that's called עומד מרובה על הפרוץ. omed meruba
al haparutz. Meaning if you have a majority of a wall closed
off, it's considered like a continued... like you've got that side is
walled off. Okay, so that should therefore make it allowed and therefore
it should be okay once it is anything less than eight אמות.
amot. וקל וחומר מחצר, Vekal vachomer mechatzar, and we can make a
קל וחומר kal vachomer from a חצר. chatzer. Now what I want...
have to tell you here is the following. The חצר chatzer in
practical terms is where houses... like I said, you have your little
houses, right, opening up into the courtyard. And the הלכה halacha of
a חצר chatzer is that, remember the גמרא Gemara before emphasized that
a מבוי mavoy is permissible with a... by a לחי lechi or
a קורה, korah, right, meaning just something minimal. By a חצר, chatzer,
the גמרא Gemara says you need a פס ארבע. pas arba. You
need a... actual like a plank, a partition of... of four טפחים,
tefachim, okay? So that's what you need by a חצר. chatzer. So
the... now the... so that's the basic idea. מבוי Mavoy is a
לחי lechi or קורה, korah, חצר chatzer you need more, you need
a פס ארבע. pas arba. Just the way they made it, we
can worry about why later. Now, the thing though that to realize
and not confuse you, gesundheit, is that it's not really defined by
חצר chatzer versus מבוי. mavoy. When you have... remember we said that
a מבוי mavoy has to be length greater than width. As soon
as you have width greater than... so length greater than width equals
מבוי. mavoy.
Width greater than length, okay, or
equal
to length (L),
equals חצר. chatzer. Even though functionally מבוי mavoy and חצר chatzer are
very different for the reason I said, in terms of this question,
so about whether it's a לחי... lechi... whether לחי lechi or קורה,
korah, what type... what do you need for the fourth wall, and
this is פס ארבע, pas arba, what you need for the fourth
wall is a function of whether it is... it's length greater than
width then it's a little thing, if it's width greater than length
you need a... you need a bigger thing. And now you can
a little bit answer... understand Michael's question, because if the width is
greater than the length, right, so a little thing here doesn't get
noticed so much, okay? If the length is greater than the width,
right, then a little... a little היכר heker is... is better. So
when the width is greater than the length, you need something more,
you need a פס ארבע. pas arba. But it's sometimes said the
חצר chatzer needs a פס ארבע, pas arba, but it really is
a function of that. Are we having fun yet? Let's say... let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says.
So,
so now the idea that עומד מרובה על הפרוץ omed meruba al
haparutz worked for the fourth wall is a קל וחומר kal vachomer
from a חצר. chatzer. ומה חצר שאינה ניתרת בלחי וקורה, U'mah chatzer
she'ein niteres bilechi v'korah, a חצר chatzer a לחי lechi or קורה
korah is not enough for the fourth wall, it needs this פס
ארבע, pas arba, ניתרת בעומד מרובה על הפרוץ, niteres b'omed meruba al
haparutz, we know that when the fourth wall or any wall really
is majority sealed off, that counts as... well that side is sealed
off. That we know from discussions of חצר, chatzer, okay, so you'll
take that on faith. So מבוי שניתר בלחי וקורה, mavoy shenitar bilechi
v'korah, a מבוי mavoy where the fourth wall can be just a
לחי lechi or קורה korah alone, אינו דין שניתר בעומד מרובה על
הפרוץ, eino din sheniter b'omed meruba al haparutz, how much more so
should it be sufficient if the fourth wall is majority closed off?
Okay, so it's a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, look, intuitively the whole
point makes sense anyway. If the majority of the side is closed
off, but if it's true by a חצר chatzer where we have
a greater demand for the fourth side, it should certainly be true
by a מבוי. mavoy. Now the גמרא Gemara sort of tries to
argue back as in classic קל וחומר kal v'chomer fashion. The גמרא
Gemara says like this: No, one minute! מה לחצר שכן פרצתה בעשר?
mah l'chatzer sheken pirtzata b'esser? תאמר במבוי שפרצתו בארבע? tomer b'mavoi shepirtzato
b'arba?
So it says: one minute, a חצר, chatzer, if you have a
break of ten טפחים, tefachim, of ten אמות, amot, it's only a
break that is ten אמות amot is considered to be a break,
whereas by a מבוי mavoi even a break of four אמות amot
is considered a break. Now that's supposed to be a little strange
because until now we just said before that ten אמות amot was
a break. Okay, but actually we're going to find out that a
break in the wall, there is a debate about how big of
a break in a wall is a problem. By a חצר chatzer
it's clearly ten אמות, amot, by a מבוי mavoi we're actually going
to find out that there's some that say even four אמות amot
is a problem. Okay, so if you take that position that even
four אמות amot is a problem by a מבוי, mavoi, so you
see that a מבוי mavoi maybe is more stringent, so maybe עומד
מרובה על הפרוץ omed meruba al haparutz won't work? So the גמרא
Gemara says: no, קסבר רב הונא בריה
דרב יהושע מבוי נמי פרצתו בעשר. kasavar Rav Huna b'reidei d'Rav Yehoshua
mavoi nami pirtzato b'esser. No, like we had said before we turned
the page, that a מבוי mavoi also the it's only a break
with ten אמות. amot. So basically a מבוי mavoi is more lenient
than a חצר, chatzer, the fourth wall can be just a לחי
lechi or קורה, kora, the breaks are the same, it's only a
break if it's ten אמות. amot. So therefore if by a חצר
chatzer עומד מרובה על הפרוץ omed meruba al haparutz works, then for
a מבוי mavoi עומד מרובה על הפרוץ omed meruba al haparutz works.
Okay, does everybody pretty much have that? More or
less? Just say yes. Okay, the basic point there is if this
is four אמות, amot, then as long as this is less than
eight, that works. How do we know? Because we know by a
חצר chatzer that when the fourth wall or any wall is majority
sealed, it's considered to be sealed. Okay, and clearly a מבוי mavoi
is more lenient by the fourth wall than a חצר. chatzer. So
now the גמרא Gemara says: קסבר בריה דרב יהושע מבוי נמי פרצתו
בעשר. kasavar b'reidei d'Rav Yehoshua mavoi nami pirtzato b'esser. למאן אמרינן? l'man
amrinan? One minute.
רב הונא
בריה דרב יהושע Rav Huna b'reidei d'Rav Yehoshua when he was explaining,
saying that this idea that if it's less than eight אמות amot
this thing works, who was he explaining that according to? He was
explaining that according to רב הונא. Rav Huna. רב הונא Rav Huna
was the one that made the statement that the לחי lechi changes
its identity at four אמות, amot, that when it gets to be
four אמות amot wide it stops being a לחי. lechi. And then
רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, Rav Huna b'reidei d'Rav Yehoshua, who was
רב הונא Rav Huna's student, it gets confusing, to רב הונא, Rav
Huna, explained that if the מבוי mavoi is less than eight, then
it actually does work. So גמרא Gemara is saying: okay, so this
is all being explained within the position of רב הונא. Rav Huna.
One minute, והא רב הונא פרצתו בארבע סבירא ליה. v'ha Rav Huna
pirtzato b'arba sevirah lei.
רב הונא Rav Huna we know says that actually a מבוי mavoi
four אמות amot is considered a break. So again if that's true
you can't learn it out from חצר. chatzer. So the גמרא Gemara
says: all this is to make the question whether you can learn
it out from חצר. chatzer. Is מבוי mavoi clearly more lenient than
חצר? chatzer? So since this is all within the position of רב
הונא Rav Huna and there's a way in which מבוי mavoi is
more strict, that a break is even by four אמות, amot, so
how come you can learn it out from חצר? chatzer? So the
גמרא Gemara says: רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע טעמא דנפשיה קאמר. Rav
Huna b'reidei d'Rav Yehoshua ta'ama d'nafshei q'amar. Fine,
he wasn't explaining it according to רב הונא, Rav Huna, he was
saying his own position. Okay, but the upshot of all of that
is that if it is four, if this four אמות amot only
becomes a problem, stops being a לחי lechi and is a wall,
but being a wall is only a problem if this is eight
or bigger. Once this is seven point nine, then most of it's
sealed off and you can learn from חצר chatzer that when most
of it is sealed off it is fine. And now the גמרא
Gemara just has one contrary opinion which is cute and let's end
with that. So the גמרא Gemara says: רב אשי אמר אפילו תימא
במבוי שמונה נמי לא צריך לחי.
Rav Ashi
amar
afilu teima b'mavoi shmonah nami lo tzarich lechi. No, I would say
even at eight you're okay, not only at
seven point nine, but exactly eight. Why? Okay, why do we say
that if it's four it's not majority sealed off? So you're in
like that's the perfect nowhere land, too big to be a לחי,
lechi, not big enough to be completely sealed off. Maybe the thickness
of the wall. Okay, one minute. So let's see what he says.
אפילו תימא במבוי שמונה נמי לא צריך לחי. afilu teima b'mavoi shmonah
nami lo tzarich lechi. ממה נפשך. manafshach. Look, make up your
mind. I'm assuming that you're not necessarily measuring precisely. So he says:
what's going on here? You think it's four אמות amot and you
think that the מבוי mavoi is exactly eight. But maybe first of
all you're off. So אי עומד נפיש, ei omed nafish, maybe the
wall, עומד omed is the part standing and פרוץ parutz is the
part that's uncovered. So maybe the part that is walled off is
really greater than the unwalled part. Then אישתרי ליה באומד מרובה על
הפרוץ, ishteirei b'omed meruba al haparutz, then it's like we've been saying,
most of the side is sealed off you're
okay. ואי פרוץ נפיש, v'ei parutz nafish, and if it's the opposite
way, that most of it is open, so that means that the
wall is less than four אמות, amot, then you're fine, אישתרי ליה
משום לחי, ishteirei mishum lechi, then you're back to being a לחי.
lechi. So מאי אמרת? mah amarta? דשוו תרוייהו כי הדדי? d'shavei tavaihu
ki hadadi?
So what are you going to say? That you actually measured it
perfectly? And it's four אמות amot and therefore it's neither a לחי
lechi because it's too big, nor does it majority seal off the
side? So he says: הוי ליה ספק דברי, havi leih safeq divrei,
first of all it's a doubt, you don't know that, it's impossible
to measure so precisely. So the one thing, the one case that
might... Maybe it was exactly precisely that case, but maybe not? So
it's all ספק, safeik, ספק דבריהם להקל. safeik divreihem l'hakel. So since
this whole issue about what we need for the fourth wall is
all דרבנן, de-rabbanan, you can be lenient and you don't have to
worry about the possibility that it was measured exactly precisely and that
you actually have here a case where it's neither one nor the
other.